# ANDY ORFALEA

(805) 570 - 4449 | aorfalea@gmail.com | Santa Barbara, CA https://www.linkedin.com/in/andy-orfalea/

https://aothree.github.io/

Motivated and resourceful data scientist with more than 10 years of senior management, as well as business administration experience. Adaptable, quick learner and always eager for the next challenge. Well versed in utilizing numbers, analysis, and visualization to discover business solutions. At my core, I'm a people person and I thrive working through collaborative and communicative team dynamics.

### **SKILLS**

**Pandas** Numpy NLP Scikit-learn Machine Learning and Deep Learning Tableau

Python **Business Strategy** 

Git/GitHub **Operations Management** 

Bilingual (Spanish)

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

**General Assembly** Remote

Data Science Immersive Fellow

January 2022 - April 2022

- 12-week, 500+ hour training program focusing on the ability to analyze, make sense of, convey data-driven facts from massive data sets, and predict what happens next through predictive modeling and pattern recognition. Description of recent projects:
  - Style of Play in the NBA Analyzing the evolution of styles of play implemented by NBA teams from 2012 to 2022, through the lens of a K-Means Clustering model.
  - o Predicting Subreddit. Web-scraped data from two different subreddits, analyzed the text using Natural Language Processing, and built a Random Forest classification model to predict which of the two subreddits a given bit of text came from.
  - Covid Vaccination Data and U.S. Politics. Clustered U.S. counties based on only county covid vaccination data. Then using that same data, built a stacking classification model to predict how those counties voted in the 2020 election.

**Freebirds** Goleta, CA

General Manager

August 2011 - January 2022

- Analysis of financial statements and adjusting business strategy accordingly. Any recommendations to the owner had to be justified by statistical analysis.
- Accounts Payable. Ensuring 30+ vendors were paid in a timely manner.
- Administered and processed payroll, requiring accuracy of record keeping and timeliness to ensure compliance with all applicable state and federal laws.
- Managing 60+ employees including development and performance review.
- Recruiting and hiring. Interviewing, onboarding, and training.
- Food quality. Responsible for upholding the restaurant's extremely high standards for freshness and flavor. Developed systems to numerically evaluate and record the quality of ingredients.

#### Assistant Manager

June 2008 - August 2011

- Projecting hourly sales, for every hour of operation, based on detailed analysis of historical sales data & trends. Based on these projections, scheduling and adjusting labor.
- Scheduling for 60+ coworkers
- Creating and re-formatting forms to analyze data using Microsoft Excel and Google Sheets.
- Maintaining and troubleshooting issues for computers, points of sale and surveillance systems.

# **EDUCATION**

General Assembly

Data Science Certificate

Boston College Bachelor of Arts, English Remote January 2022 - April 2022

Boston, Massachusetts September 2004 – May 2008